okay well sir it's a great example of
how mushrooms can be involved in healing
the soil and but mushrooms are also for
millions of years have been used for
healing human beings can you give it an
example medicinal mushroom use that
would be particularly informative the
the mushroom specie that meal comes to
mind for a medicinal use but
historically in modern times as a
gerakan Fahmy topsis officinalis which
deities first described in 65 ad as a
treatment against consumption and other
respiratory illnesses later thought to
be known tuberculosis so 2,000 years ago
in the first materia medica the very
first pharmacopoeia officinalis is the
official medicine of choice that's why
it's called officinalis and for 2,000
years this mushroom was used
there's also called the quinine fungus
doesn't have quinine but it has a chalk
like appearance it grows the size of a
beehive and as the oldest growing
mushroom in the environment that I know
grows for up to 100 years under really
inclement weather conditions and the
Alps of Austria now thought to be
extinct largely in Europe and Washington
State Oregon Northern California and in
British Columbia Canada and we have gone
into your growth forests collecting this
mushroom we now have a library of 37
strains the largest library by a factor
of 10 I think of anyone in the world and
we're trying to save the species from
extinction we were working with a
biology old program the US Defense
Department dropped after 9/11 I sent
hundreds of samples to the US
government's Bioshield
bio defense program because the US
government and other governments
recognized that bioterrorism by far was
the biggest uncontrolled threat viruses
don't care about borders if you had 10
al-qaida infected with smallpox coming
through different borders and making
contact you know at food stands and
restrooms through contact with crowded
people we could have a pandemic of
smallpox after 1968 no one's no one's
been immunized so smallpox was the
number one virus a concern by the US
Defense Department we sent hundreds of
extracts because of my cultural library
was recognized as being unique and lo
and behold the results came back and the
anti smallpox
properties were localized in a gerakan
now what a lot of people may not
understand is when you get viral
infections oftentimes bacterial
infections ensue and so the virus harms
your immune system it can you know with
flu viruses can scar your lungs and then
bacterial infections ensue well gerakan
was used to fight largely bacterial
infections and in according to
historical record we know very little
about its actual use I'm sure at the
Library of Alexandria
there have been halt homes on a gerakan
and it's used probably but the fact that
the Agera con has dual antiviral and
antibacterial properties and has a 2,000
year history of use is a real strong
testimonial of a mushroom growing and
endangered habitats like the old-growth
forests that if we we protect and we
invest in the protection of that species
and understand it better we could save
literally millions of lives and in the
past four weeks my collaborators at the
National Center for natural products
research the University of Minnesota
Mississippi dr. Susan Manley dr. semir
Ross Shabana
caw-caw finally after more than five
years of bio guided fractionation we
have identified a cluster of novel
antiviral compounds heretofore
undiscovered that are active against
viruses when we sent these extracts of
agaric on to test against flu viruses we
also had an exceptionally high activity
now exceptional high activity of a
natural extract against positive
controls which are pure pharmaceuticals
at the same concentrations so our
natural extracts obviously have
something in them that's very very
powerful so here is you know those are
that's a real clear example how one
mushroom in the old-growth forests what
people may not understand is that we
share in common many of the same
pathogens that afflict mushrooms so
Staphylococcus streptococcus ecoli they
also attack mushroom mycelium and so the
host defensive resistance of the
mycelium against us pathogens we can
also benefit from the fact that this
fungus is dually active against an RNA
virus like flu viruses DNA virus like
small
parks as a conundrum and it may be that
there's not a category of medicine yet
to describe something this duly active
against both sets of viruses because
typically has thought to be a toxin not
a medicine but the fact that we know it
is less toxic than siddhattha vir and
ribavirin but far more potent than
there's two pharmaceuticals you know is
a testimonial that we've found something
quite interesting and new so we've been
approved for small mammal studies and I
think one thing we can be assured of and
it's a prediction I will make that will
be unfortunately be true is that as
ecosystems are impaired we will have
endemic storms we're gonna have them
increasingly happening we have this
massive flood in Pakistan we have a new
bacteria that has a transponder gene
coming out of New Delhi from cosmetic
surgery if that transponder gene gives
makes all bacteria resistant to all
known antibiotics this is not a good
thing
and so we are on the edge of a pandemic
storms that will hit us from different
directions unless we can increase our
hosts defensive resistance by investing
in biodiversity by investing in fungi
that create the soils that give
biodiversity unless we do all of that
you know our time on this planet may be
of quite limited